Unknown: Styling your site with global<br />styles. Learning Outcome, change global
styles to reflect your own brand. Change<br />typography, colors layout, using the
font library feature, how to apply a<br />color palette change to an accent color,
change the global style of blocks<br />example of quote block. A couple of
resources to think about beforehand is<br />font pairing. A good design principle is
to pick a one style of font for your<br />heading and a different font style for
your text. Here's an article from Google<br />Fonts. Another resource is the font pair
website FONTPAIR. Within their pairings<br />tab, they've paired together fonts that
work well. Color Palettes is another<br />thing to think about before designing.
Here are two resources that have free<br />access Coolors has a trending color
palette, which will give you the hex<br />code number, which is always good to jot
down so that you have those colors.<br />Canva also has a color palette that's
free. We're gonna go to our dashboard<br />now. And we'll look at our site toolbar
on the left, and go down to Appearance<br />and over to editor and click on that.
We'll go in under design, and go to<br />styles. Click on that. And within the
style Styles menu, you will see an icon<br />which is the style book and we'll talk
about that in a later lesson. And the<br />pencil icon which when I hover over says
Edit style. So we'll click on that.<br />We're going to look at browse styles now.
I opened up my right menu at the upper<br />right hand corner is a halfmoon. And I
hover over in that that says styles. So<br />I'm going to go down to browse styles.
The 2024 theme comes with eight<br />variations. The variations include
different color and font combinations.<br />When I click on one of the variations, I
can see instantly how the different<br />blocks will look on my site. I'm going
to stick with the default theme. And<br />we'll look at maybe changing a couple of
the colors to better represent my color<br />palette. Then go back out to the Style
section. Typography. So we're going to<br />look at our typography section. This
section manages the settings for font<br />families size appearance, from text to
links to buttons. A good rule of design<br />is to have, like I said before one font
family for headings and a different plug<br />compatible font family for the text. A
new feature is our presets, we can look<br />at the different font combinations. And
if we wanted to change those, even<br />though I'm in the default theme, I can
still change the fonts, how I would<br />like. The fonts that come with the theme
are listed here. And you see that I have<br />different combinations variants. So that
means I have to wear variations of this<br />one and two variations of this one. A
new feature is to manage your fonts. And<br />if you hover over this icon, I'm going
to open up the font library. So the<br />theme fonts are listed. Like I said, I
also have the option to upload or<br />install fonts. So let's look at install
fonts first, and we're going to connect<br />to Google fonts. So we need to allow
access to our to the Google fonts and we<br />can scroll through and there are 390
pages as of this recording, so there's a<br />lot to choose from. So I had done a
little bit of research. And so I know<br />that I like this one particular, Open
Sans. So I'm gonna click on that. Now<br />the Open Sans, I'm gonna use for my main
text. So I don't need follow these. And<br />so I'm planning ahead that I need a, at
least a normal, and I like it a little<br />bit darker than the 300 normal. So I'm
going to pick the 400, I'd like to be<br />able to make some words a little bit
bold. So I'm going to pick the 700. I'm<br />also going to pick an italic, again, the
400 and a bold with that, so I have four<br />of those. So I'm going to hit click
Install button at the bottom. And if I<br />scroll back up, it says that it was
successful. So when I go back to the<br />library tab, I see that install fonts, I
have my font there, and I have the four<br />variants active. The other way to upload
is to upload. So I'm going to click on<br />Upload. And just to remember that upload
fonts appear and can be used, it needs<br />to be support, you need to use a
supportive format of a TTF, OTF, WOFF or<br />a WOFF two format. So in the middle is
the word upload font, I'm going to click<br />on that. And I already have a folder of
a font that I like, I'm going to open<br />that font. And again, I don't need all
of them. But this is going to be the<br />font for my headings. So I definitely
want to have a regular and I don't need<br />any light. I'm definitely would like a
bold, because my headings I'd like to<br />make bold. So I think I'm going to just
stick with that because I don't want to<br />do any italic headings and stuff like
that. So, again, I'm planning ahead of<br />time, but is that beneficial for these
steps. So the font was successful, I'm<br />going to go back to my library, and I
see that that font is available now. So<br />I can close this up. And if I look over
on my right menu, I see that I have<br />those two options available for me too.
The other section down here is the<br />elements. So I can go in and on a global
level, change all of my text. So now<br />that I've added these two new fonts, I'm
going to go into text. And I want to<br />change it to the Open Sans. Okay. And
then I want to keep it regular. Okay. So<br />we're good with that, we're going to
click Save. And it's going to save that,<br />and I'm going to click back out and go
into my headings. And so now the<br />headings have different so I could do
all of my headings, the same font<br />family, okay. But remember that we have
one h one per page, and then we have to<br />do our structural formatting, then the
next one would be an h two. And then we<br />would go into h threes, and so on. So
you see that there are different sizes<br />of the font. So I probably want to kind
of go through and style each of the<br />font, double check the sizing of that is
the default sizing isn't what I would<br />like if I would like maybe the H threes
to be a little bit bigger font, I can do<br />that here. So let's look at this. We
want to change our font family to<br />Bellota and I want to make it the bold
Okay, and I'm gonna go a little bit<br />bigger than extra large because the font
family is on the smaller sites. I'm<br />going to click on this we're using rems
Rem is just an easier to when you when<br />it goes down to mobile, that it sizes a
little bit better. So let's go to a 4.5.<br />So you can see the difference up in this
little window at the top. I'm not seeing<br />any change over here. It might be just a
little bug within there, so I'm going to<br />click on that and save it and save
again. And then I can go to, like I<br />said, the h two is okay.
And we can go to the all? And I need to<br />make sure that well, no, yeah, no, yeah,
let's just see, you can always change<br />your design in the middle, right? The h
two, I'm going to keep in the Bellota.<br />And then like that side, so I'm gonna
say that, let me go back. Because I<br />don't want all the font to be, can I
just realize that I wouldn't want the H<br />threes to be the fancier font. So the H
threes, we're going to just make as the<br />Open Sans. But I do want to make it a
little bit bigger. Okay, so I'm gonna do<br />that. And let's just look at our front
end to see what happens there. So we've<br />changed that to the bold that too, and
that is staying. So things to play with<br />on that. So I'm going to click back out
of typography.
The next section is colors. So our color<br />section takes care of kind of fine
tuning our color palettes that we<br />picked. Remember that I picked the
default, and the default palette has 10<br />colors. Now if I've gotten this far, and
I might want to change to one of the<br />other ones, or just at least see how it
is. I do have access to it right above.<br />So if I click on the 10 colors of the
color palette, we have the palette, we<br />have our solid and we have our gradient,
my focus just more on the solid right<br />now. And like I said, there was one
color this orange that I probably will<br />not use, but I did want to kind of
change that. So I can go into themes and<br />the three dots over here. Click and it
says Show Details. Okay. So the close up<br />is going to show after I've changed the
color. So the reset colors will appear<br />in that, as of right now where I'm at on
here, it just shows the show details. So<br />I'm going to click on Show Details. And
what's nice is that it shows the names<br />of the different colors. And so I want
to focus in on accent number three. So<br />if I click on that, I can go ahead and
change the color. I'm gonna change it to<br />more of a bright red, a deeper red.
Okay, so I found that I'm happy with<br />that it's changed. And then I have to
make sure I hit done. And then hit save.<br />Okay, so on doing the color setting,
it's nice to kind of just double check<br />to make sure what you have changed. So
don't just keep looking. Alright, so I<br />can also add a custom color if I wanted
to add more colors within here. So now<br />that we go back out to from our palette,
we go back to our colors menu.
The section down below is our colors.<br />Okay, so we have. We can pick our basic
text background heading, we could also<br />do the H ones and stuff too. Okay. So
what we want to do is the button. So I'd<br />like to change that one up and have it
as a universal color. So if I click on<br />the button colors, I have the option for
the text in the background and<br />gradients. So let's look at the text. So
right now it's white, and I know that<br />we're going to kind of keep that so then
look at our background and we're gonna<br />change that to red. Okay, so now we're
good with that. So then we make sure we<br />hit save up here and that will change
the global styles of the button and the<br />color setting. So then whenever I add a
button, it will be that those two colors<br />right we're gonna go back out.
Our next section is layout. Alright, so<br />we go down to layout. And the layout
section styles the main content area,<br />and gives the content and the wide in
pixels. Okay, so that is from your left<br />to all the way to your right. These are
the default settings. So you see that<br />there is some padding already part of
it. And if you take a look up here in<br />the heading, and I moved this, you can
see how that changes. Okay, we also have<br />a block spacing, default, that's already
set there, too. So I click back out of layout.
Blocks is our next section. We will go<br />down here to blocks and this menu opens
up all of our blocks that are within<br />this theme. And we can go in and we can
customize the appearance of specific<br />blocks and for the whole site. So that
means that if you want all your heading<br />blocks to have a certain background
color, you could do that. Okay, you<br />don't want to get too involved with
doing each of these separately, because<br />remember, we have our initial global
styles up here that we've already<br />changed. And if you start changing every
little block, then it gets really<br />confusing when you need to do change
something, you don't know where you<br />changed it. So it's always good to start
in the global styles. And then if<br />there's a particular block that you
really want to kind of change, and you<br />could do that. So I'm gonna just give an
example of the quote block because<br />that's kind of like a specialty block
that you might want to do a different<br />kind of font. So let's scroll down here
to my example. So we have the quote<br />block. I've added a group and the quote
block has a paragraph within it. And<br />then it has an area for citation which
is the author's name. So if I want to<br />change the font of this, okay, I can go
to typography and go down to font. And<br />remember that I have my Open Sans as my
overall font. And I can either do it as<br />regular or I can do it as italic. Things
like that. And I can always change the<br />size of it to if I just want it small,
large, I can click on Save for that. So<br />that would be an example.
I just touched on the basics of how to<br />style your site with global styles. Go
explore on your site and check out more<br />lessons.